Did you ever wonder if certain foods
have a direct effect on your health?
Well, I’m here to
solve that mystery
since you are
the foods you eat.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
In this series, we look at the history,
benefits, and safety of water fluoridation.
And we start by looking at the efficacy
of adding fluoride to the water supply.
A meta-analysis
of all the studies
on the dental health
implications
of vegetarian diets
showed significantly
fewer decayed teeth,
missing teeth,
and the number of teeth
with fillings.
One of the studies
that bucked the trend
and showed that
vegetarians had more cavities
blamed the excess decay
on the fact that vegetarians
were significantly
less likely to choose
fluoride-containing toothpaste,
supported by the fact
that those who did use
toothpaste with fluoride
had significantly fewer
decayed teeth
than those who didn't.
Fluoride is thought to protect
teeth by improving the intrinsic
stability of the mineral
structure of dental enamel.
A recent meta-analysis of nearly
100 randomized controlled trials
of fluoride toothpaste involving
more than 10,000 people
found "high-certainty" evidence
that toothpaste containing
the typical amount of fluoride
reduces tooth decay
significantly more
than non-fluoride toothpaste
in both children and adults.
But what about the addition
of fluoride to the water supply?
A medical consensus
of public health authorities
around the world
has considered
water fluoridation
at appropriate levels
as a safe and effective means
to prevent cavities
on a community-wide scale.
In fact, the CDC,
the US Centers for Disease
Control and Prevention,
deemed fluoridation
of drinking water
as one of the top ten
public health achievements
of the 20th century.
However, community
water fluoridation
has long been a flashpoint
of polemic and polarization.
Anti-fluoridation activists
underscore that there is
no human dietary
requirement for fluoride
and argue that
water fluoridation
isn't effective enough
to justify the costs,
which may include health risks.
First, some background before
I dive into the controversy.
Fluoride is a mineral element
in the Earth's crust
that naturally occurs
in most water supplies.
This is one of the reasons
fluoridation has withstood
Constitutional challenges.
Courts have ruled that,
rather than an added medication,
fluoride can be seen as
a nutrient found naturally
in some areas but not others,
and fluoridation
of water supplies
is a matter of just
leveling the playing field,
particularly for
poor communities
who may have limited access
to dental care.
Fluoridation can be defined as
"the upward
or downward adjustment
of the level of fluoride
content in drinking water
to an optimal level
just enough to prevent cavities
but not enough
to cause fluorosis,"
or cosmetic changes
to the teeth.
It all started in 1901
with an investigation
into Colorado Brown Stain,
"grotesque" brown stains
on the teeth
of Colorado Springs residents.
At the same time, teeth
afflicted by the condition were
"surprisingly and inexplicably
resistant to decay."
After fluoride was identified
as the basis for these changes,
a nationwide survey of fluoride
levels in drinking water
in the 1930s
led to the discovery
that fluoride could reach levels
around 1 part per million
without causing
serious fluorosis.
Hoping to get
the best of both worlds,
Grand Rapids, Michigan, in 1945,
became the first city
in the world
to fluoridate its water supply.
Within 11 years, cavity rates
among children in Grand Rapids
were reportedly down
more than 60 percent,
and a fluoridation
movement was born.
Today, about two dozen countries
fluoridate their drinking water.
Dozens of others have
naturally fluoridated water
or instead add fluoride
to milk or table salt.
Fluoridation pushback
started almost immediately
in the United States.
The obsession
of Dr. Strangelove's
Colonel Ripper with the purity
of his "precious bodily fluids"
was based on real-life
right-wing Red Scare
conspiracy theories
that fluoridation
was meant to produce
"moronic, atheistic slaves"
who would bow to the communists.
Today's social media
is also rife
with anti-fluoridation messages.
Studies have found that 63
percent of Instagram posts
regarding fluoride could be
classified as anti-fluoride,
64 percent of tweets on Twitter,
99 percent of YouTube videos,
and up to 100 percent
of fluoride groups and pages
found on Facebook
were anti-fluoride.
Years before COVID,
the antifluoridation crusade
was considered a case study
of "digital pandemics of
public health misinformation."
In the year before COVID,
the first worldwide survey
of the crisis of confidence
in science
of 140,000 people
in 140 countries
found that only
18 percent of humanity
appeared to have a "high" level
of trust in science.
To my pleasant surprise though,
despite so many
institutional failures,
a 2020 follow-up of the survey
found trust in science
actually increased after COVID.
Where does the science land
on water fluoridation?
First, let me address efficacy.
The CDC attributes the steep
decline in dental decay
in the United States in the
latter half of the 20th century
to water fluoridation,
but similar declines were noted
in non-fluoridated countries,
attributed in large part to the
widespread global distribution
of fluoride toothpaste.
The best evidence we have
comes from prospective studies
with concurrent controls,
comparing cavity rates over time
in fluoridated versus
non-fluoridated populations.
There have been more than 100
such studies to date,
and overall,
fluoridation results in
35 percent fewer decayed,
missing, or filled baby teeth
and 26 percent fewer
decayed, missing,
or filled permanent teeth.
So, community fluoridation
does indeed help
to cut down on cavities.
The question then becomes,
at what cost,
which we'll discuss next.
Naturally
fluoridated waters
up around two parts per million
can put children
under the age of nine
at increased risk
for dental fluorosis,
and a lifetime of drinking water
at four ppm can cause
skeletal fluorosis and increase
the risk of bone fractures.
You can see these kinds of
levels in the Earth's natural
fluoride belts that extend
from Turkey through Iraq, Iran,
and Afghanistan
to China and Japan.
The reason susceptibility
to dental fluorosis ends
at around eight years old
is that's when enamel
maturation is completed,
before our final permanent teeth
finish erupting.
After teeth are formed,
dental fluorosis can no longer
develop or worsen.
At one ppm, one part
per million of fluoride,
public health authorities
estimated that less than
10 percent of kids
would develop the condition,
and only in its mildest forms.
We've since learned that
the prevalence and severity
of fluorosis is much higher
than predicted.
According to the CDC,
about a third of American
children now have some form
of dental fluorosis,
with about one in 30
experiencing
a moderate to severe case.
This may reflect exposure
to multiple fluoride sources
not factored into
the original calculations.
Now, most fluorosis is so mild
as to be hardly noticeable,
taking the form
of white streaks or splotches
visible only to dentists
under the bright lights
of their exam chair.
But serious cases can involve
severe pitting and discoloration
and present more than just
a cosmetic defect.
For example, one study found
that children with severe cases
are more likely to be viewed by
their peers as less attractive,
less careful, less clean,
less happy, less healthy,
less intelligent, less kind,
less reliable, less social.
Imagine what that could do
to a kid's self-esteem.
Given the higher-than-expected
rates of fluorosis,
in 2015,
the U.S. Public Health Service
reduced the recommended fluoride
concentration of drinking water
down to 0.7 ppm
across the board.
Previously, levels were set at
up to 1.2 ppm in cooler areas
where people tend
to drink less water.
This change would be estimated
to keep the percentage
of those developing fluorosis
of "aesthetic concern"
down to approximately
12 percent.
In terms of other health
concerns, until recently,
mainstream medicine's view might
have perhaps best been summed up
by the final statement in
an exhaustive report published
by Consumer Reports in 1978:
"The simple truth is that
there is no
scientific controversy
over the safety of fluoridation.
The practice is safe,
economical, and beneficial.
The survival
of this fake controversy,
in the Consumer Union's opinion,
is one of the major triumphs
of quackery over science
in our generation."
In the last few years, though,
there have been growing concerns
about the adverse effects
of fluoride
on brain development,
which I'll address next.
Fluoridehad been found to be
a developmental neurotoxin
in rats and mice,
leading to learning
and memory deficits,
which led to an interest
in studying human populations.
Starting in the 1980s,
reports started appearing
in Chinese medical journals
that found correlations
between areas
naturally containing higher
fluoride levels in water
with lower intelligence
among children.
Dental fluorosis, the
fluoride-induced tooth mottling,
is widespread in China,
with more than
90 million residents affected,
often in small pockets
surrounding particular
small springs
or mountain sources.
Researchers took
advantage of the fact
that even adjoining
neighborhoods could have
wildly different
fluoride exposure,
setting up a type
of natural experiment.
Due to limited access
to Chinese journals at the time,
these studies largely
escaped the attention
of scientists in the West
until a meta-analysis
of 16 such studies
was published in English
in 2008.
"Fluoride and Children's
Intelligence: A Meta-analysis"
found that children living
in areas prone to fluorosis
had five times higher odds
of developing low IQ
than those living in areas
with little or no fluorosis.
So, here we were,
thinking dental fluorosis
was just a cosmetic blemish,
but it may instead
be a visual indicator
of intellectual deficits.
A subsequent
meta-analysis in 2012
including about 10 more studies
found that the average
intelligence gap between
high and low fluoride exposure
areas was about seven IQ points.
By far the largest study,
involving thousands of children,
it found that even
at fluoride levels below 1 ppm,
higher fluoride levels
were associated with
a large drop
in the chances of developing
excellent intelligence,
defined as an IQ
of 130 or higher.
Even very mild fluorosis was
associated with less than half
the odds of reaching
such a high IQ.
By now, there have been
more than 50 studies showing
an association between higher
fluoride exposure and lower IQ.
In the latest systematic
review meta-analysis,
90 percent of the studies
published in the last ten years
reported a link between
high fluoride exposure
and reduced intelligence.
However, serious caveats
are in order.
First, the fluoride
concentrations
in most of these studies
were well above
fluoridation levels.
In the 2012 meta-analysis,
for example, one study clocked
concentrations
as high as 11.5 ppm,
far exceeding the US target
of 0.7 parts per million
as well as
the average concentration
in the United States,
which is around 0.8 ppm
in municipal water
and 0.3 ppm in well water.
Now, to be fair,
the 11.5 ppm in the
meta-analysis was an outlier.
The average elevated level
was only about
two parts per million,
and most found
associated IQ decrements
below the EPA's upper limit,
its Maximum Contaminant Level
Goal of four ppm,
which is supposed
to represent the level
"below which there is no known
or expected risk to health."
Some studies showed
lower intelligence
with fluoride concentrations
even down at one to two ppm
with one estimate suggesting
the smallest harmful
concentration,
potentially shaving off
a single IQ point,
would be down around 0.3 ppm,
assuming you drink
four cups of water a day,
while others suggest
it's too early to be able
to calculate a threshold
for human neurotoxicity
due to insufficient
available data.
The second major caveat
is confounding.
Nearly all of the studies
to date have been performed
in rural communities
in countries like China,
Iran, and Mongolia.
Areas within these countries
with unusually high
fluoride levels
may be particularly
poor and underdeveloped,
since relatively
rich communities
may be more likely to invest
in higher-quality drinking water
that filters out fluoride,
if only to reduce
dental fluorosis.
High fluoride water may also be
more likely to be contaminated
with other neurotoxins.
Fluoride exists in water as
a negatively charged particle.
To maintain electroneutrality,
this may pull
into the groundwater
positively charged particles
such as aluminum,
arsenic, lead, or mercury.
This doesn't happen
in community water fluoridation
since the negative fluoride ions
are balanced out
in the water treatment process.
Finally,
most of the older studies
were cross-sectional
and ecological,
meaning they looked
at a snapshot-in-time
of group level data rather than
individual-exposures-over-time.
Just because a child with low IQ
lives in a high fluoride area
doesn't necessarily mean
they or their mom actually
drank the water, for example.
Ideally, we'd be able to measure
individual exposure levels
and then follow
the kids over time
to see if those
with higher exposure
really do grow up
with stunted intellects.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now,
which premiered at #2 on the
New York Times Best Sellers list.
Check it out at your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is itself a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.